{
  "reference_number": "12219",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": "NZ has delayed for far too long. We need to set the boldest deadlines now."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "Choosing this option sends a strong message that we need to make changes ourselves and not expect others to do it for us. There\n\n would still be the possibility of drawing on overseas emissions reductions if there was a significant emergency."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "This is simple pragmatism. But the circumstances need to be clearly and carefully described so that this does not provide a\n government with \"carte blanche\" to revise targets downwards."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - the third emissions budget should be able to be changed but only when the subsequent budget is set",
      "answer_index": 4,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Pragmatism again. But (again) definition of \"exceptional circumstances\" is absolutely essential. Rather than define natural disasters as\n\n an exceptional circumstance, it would be necessary to define how a particular circumstance makes it IMPOSSIBLE for us to meet our\nbudgets."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "The most important issues are: (1) transport and (2) land use. With regard to land use, it is essential that the government consult\nvery widely (not just the standard, \"business-as-usual\" interests) but \"fringe\" groups, eg. organics; farm forestry; Tane's Tree Trust;\n\nsmall farmers; Biological Husbandry Unit at Lincoln, etc. This is where the real potential for innovation will come from."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "The CCC should also be required (in collaboration with other agencies, where appropriate) to disseminate information in a concise\nand readable form so that the general public can keep up to date with action in NZ and around the world. The CCC should be\n\nrequired to provide specific advice on investment in research into alternatives to conventional land use practices (e.g. hemp)."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": "Must also consider whether ETS is the appropriate long-term mechanism, rather than others (especially a Carbon Tax)."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I would specify that someone with wide-ranging expertise in land use is essential. This could need more than one person (eg.\nsomeone with agricultural background and someone with forestry background). Most important of all, they should be INDEPENDENT\nOF EXISTING INDUSTRY GROUPS."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "The CCC must take very seriously the second challenge (p.19): \"significant changes to our energy, transport and agricultural\nsectors\". While holding fast to targets and budgets, the CCC's advisory function must include practical alternatives for industry and\n\nagricultural interest groups to pursue."
    }
  ]
}
